Hello, and welcome to Lesson 13 of this introduction to calculus with Wolfram U.
大家好，欢迎来到本次与沃尔夫兰大学合作的微积分入门第13课。
The topic for this lesson is rates of change in the sciences.
本节课的主题是科学的变化率。
Let’s begin with a brief overview of the lesson.
我们先来简单介绍一下本课的内容。
Let’s say you have a particle which moves along a straight line, for example.
比如说，你有一个沿着直线运动的粒子。
The position at time t is given by this function s[t] that’s t^3 + 2t – 2. Now once you have
时间t的位置由这个函数s[t]给出，即t^3 + 2t - 2。现在一旦你有
the position as a function of time, what you can do is to compute the derivative,
位置作为时间的函数，你可以做的是计算导数。
and then that will give you the velocity of the particle at time t. Here’s velocity. That’s 3t^2 + 2.
然后就可以得到粒子在时间t的速度。这就是速度。就是3t^2+2。
Once you have both s and v, you can then work out their values at any time. For example,
一旦你有了s和v，你就可以随时计算出它们的值。例如：&lt;i&gt;s&lt;/i&gt;和&lt;i&gt;v&lt;/i&gt;，你就可以随时计算出它们的值。
at t = 10, the values are 1,018 and 302. Having done that, you can also plot
在t=10时，数值分别为1,018和302。做完这些后，您还可以绘制
the position and velocity as a function of time over a certain period of time—in this case,
在一定时期内，位置和速度作为时间的函数，在这种情况下。
from 0 to 20. In this very simple example, you see that the derivative gives you
从0到20。在这个非常简单的例子中，你可以看到导数给你的是
a nice way of approaching a problem in mechanics. What we’ll do in this lesson is
一种很好的解决力学问题的方法。这节课我们要做的是
to explore the applications of differential calculus in the sciences in various different ways.
来探讨微分微积分在科学中各种不同方式的应用。
Let’s again take up an example in mechanics where you have the position being given
让我们再举一个力学中的例子，在这个例子中，你有一个位置被赋予了
as a function of time like over here. You could work out the velocity of course
作为时间的函数，就像在这里。当然，你可以计算出速度
as the first derivative, but you could also work out the acceleration, which is the second derivative.
作为第一导数，但你也可以计算出加速度，这是第二导数。
Once we have done that, we could ask questions. For example, you could ask
做完这些，我们就可以提问了。例如，你可以问
when is the particle at rest? Well, it’s at rest when the velocity is 0. You could solve that equation
粒子何时处于静止状态？当速度为0时，它就处于静止状态，你可以解这个等式
and find out that the particle is at rest when t is either 2/3 or 2. Then you can plot the position,
并找出当t为2/3或2时，粒子处于静止状态。然后就可以绘制位置图了。
the velocity and the acceleration and get their graphs. You see that the position is given by
速度和加速度，并得到它们的图形。你可以看到，位置是由
the blue graph over here. The velocity is the graph over there, and it clearly intersects
这里的蓝色图形。速度是那边的图，很明显地与之相交了
the time axis at around 2/3 and 2. The acceleration is a linear function of time.
的时间轴在2/3左右，2。加速度是时间的线性函数。
The derivative is a very powerful way of studying problems in mechanics.
导数是研究力学中问题的一种非常有力的方法。
Let’s go on to another example where let’s say you want to talk about the linear density of a rod.
我们再来看看另一个例子，比如说你想讨论一个杆子的线性密度。
Now if you have a rod and, let’s say, it’s got mass m and a certain length,
现在，如果你有一根杆子，比方说，它有质量m和一定的长度。
then the average linear density is simply the mass divided by the length.
那么平均线密度就是简单的质量除以长度。
But of course what could happen is that the mass of the rod depends upon how far down
但当然，可能发生的情况是，杆子的质量取决于多大程度上的下降。
you are on it. Let’s say the mass might be the cube root of the length, and in that case,
你在上面。比方说，质量可能是长度的立方根，这样的话。
you can talk about the linear density at a given length l. That is given by the derivative of the mass
你可以谈论给定长度l的线性密度。那是由质量的导数给出的
with respect to l. In this case, it’s 1/(3³√(l^2)). Then of course you can work out the linear density
相对于l。在这种情况下，它是1/(3³√(l^2))。当然，你可以计算出线性密度
at any given length. In this case, if the length is 10, the answer is about 0.07.
在任何给定的长度上。在这种情况下，如果长度是10，答案约为0.07。
Then you can plot both the mass and the linear density. You see that the mass sort of has
然后你可以绘制质量和线性密度。你会发现质量有点像
constant increase, but the linear density goes down as the length increases
不断增加，但随着长度的增加，线性密度会下降
because of this expression for the derivative.
因为这个导数的表达式。
Okay. Let’s go on now to current. If you have, let’s say, a wire
好吧，我们现在就来看看电流。我们现在继续说说电流。如果你有，比方说，一个电线，你可以用它来代替。
and some current flows through it, then the average current is the charge that flows
和一些电流流过它，那么平均电流就是流过的电荷。
in a certain period of time. But of course the charge itself might depend upon the time t
在一定时间内。当然，充电本身可能取决于时间t。
like over here, and then the current at any given instant will be the derivative of that charge
就像这里一样，然后在任何一个瞬间的电流将是该电荷的导数。
with respect to t. At, let’s say, one second, the current is 4 amperes. Then what you can do is
相对于t。在，比方说，一秒钟，电流是4安培。那么你可以做的是
to plot the charge and the current and get back a plot for both these quantities.
绘制电荷和电流，并得到这两个量的曲线图。
Let’s go on now to chemistry. Now in chemistry, one talks about reactions—chemical reactions.
现在我们继续讲化学。现在在化学中，人们谈论的是反应--化学反应。
What happens there is that one or more reactants would undergo some process
在那里发生的事情是，一个或多个反应物将经历一些过程。
and give you some products.  For example, you might have two reactants A and B
并给你一些产品。例如，你可能有两个反应物A和B。
that give you a product C. One talks about the concentration of any of these in moles per liter.
赋予你一个产品C。人们谈论其中任何一种的浓度，都是以摩尔/升为单位的。
That concentration is of course a function of time as time goes by. For example, A and B might
当然，随着时间的推移，这种浓度是时间的函数。例如，A和B可能是
decrease in quantity and C might go up. In that case, the rate of reaction at an instant is given by
数量减少，C可能会上升。在这种情况下，某一瞬间的反应速率由以下公式给出。
the derivative of the concentration with respect to t. For example, suppose that
浓度相对于t的导数。例如，假设
the concentration of C is given by 3t/(3t + 1). Then the rate of reaction at any given time
C的浓度由3t/(3t+1)给出。那么在任何给定时间内的反应速率
is a derivative, so it’s 3/(1 + 3t)^2. Then what you can do is to plot both these quantities,
是一个导数，所以它是3/(1+3t)^2。那么你能做的就是把这两个量都画出来。
and you see that as time goes by, the concentration will increase, but of course
随着时间的推移，你会看到，浓度会增加，但当然... ...
the rate of reaction will go down as the system approaches a steady state.
当系统接近稳定状态时，反应速度将下降。
Okay. Let’s go on now to biology. In biology, one talks about population models.
好了，现在我们继续讲生物。我们现在继续说说生物学。在生物学上，人们谈论的是种群模型。
For example, the population at time t might be given by 2t^3 + t, and in that case,
例如，时间t时的人口可能由2t^3+t给出，在这种情况下：
the growth rate for that population is the derivative of that population with respect to t.
该人口的增长率是该人口相对于t的导数。
In this case, it’s just 6t^2 + 1. Then of course you can plot both the population and the growth rate
在这种情况下，只是6t^2+1。那么你当然可以同时绘制人口和增长率的图谱
like we’ve done over here. In practice, one might have a slightly different model.
就像我们在这边做的那样。在实践中，可能会有稍微不同的模式。
For example, if you talk about the growth of bacteria, then it might happen that
例如，如果你说到细菌的生长，那么可能会发生以下情况
the population doubles every minute, for example, in which case
比如说，人口每分钟翻一番，在这种情况下
you might get a formula like the initial population times 2^t,
你可能会得到一个公式，如初始人口乘以2^t。
and that’s what is called an exponential function.
这就是所谓的指数函数。
Okay. Finally, let’s go on to economics. In economics, one talks about the cost function.
好吧，最后，我们来谈谈经济。最后，我们继续说说经济学。在经济学中，人们谈论的是成本函数。
Let’s say a company might talk about its cost function, which is a total cost of producing x units.
比方说，一家公司可能会谈论它的成本函数，即生产x单位的总成本。
Here’s a cost function in a particular case. Now if you find the derivative of the cost function,
这是一个特殊情况下的成本函数。现在如果你找到成本函数的导数。
then that’s what is called the marginal cost. The marginal cost, roughly speaking,
那么这就是所谓的边际成本。边际成本，粗略的说。
is the amount of money it costs to produce an extra unit. For example, you might ask
是生产一个额外单位的成本。例如，你可以问
what is the marginal cost and the actual cost of producing the 1,001st unit?
生产第1,001个单位的边际成本和实际成本是多少？
That’s going to be the derivative of the cost at that value, or you could actually find it
这将是成本在该值的导数，或者你实际上可以找到它
by subtracting off the cost in both the cases, so 1,001 – 1,000. You see that they are very close,
通过减去两种情况下的成本，所以1,001 - 1,000。你看，它们非常接近。
but not quite the same. The marginal cost gives you a very good estimate of
但又不尽相同。边际成本为你提供了一个非常好的估计。
the cost to produce an extra unit. Once again, you can plot everything over here,
生产一个额外单位的成本。再一次，你可以在这里绘制一切。
the cost and the marginal cost, to get those two plots.
成本和边际成本，得到这两块地。
Okay. That brings me to the end of this lesson. The main point is that derivatives are used
好了，我的课到此结束。这节课就到此结束了。主要的一点是，衍生工具是用来
universally in the sciences. If you’re a physicist, you might use them to study motion.
普遍存在于科学领域。如果你是物理学家，你可能会用它们来研究运动。
If you’re a chemist, you might use them to study reaction rates, but if you’re a biologist,
如果你是一个化学家，你可能会用它们来研究反应速率，但如果你是一个生物学家。
you might use them to study growth rates. Finally, it’s not just the natural sciences,
你可以用它们来研究增长率。最后，不仅仅是自然科学。
but also the social sciences. In economics, you might use derivatives to find the marginal cost.
但也是社会科学。在经济学中，你可能会使用衍生工具来寻找边际成本。
Of course, there are many more uses of derivatives that we haven’t spoken about in this lesson,
当然，衍生工具的用途还有很多，我们这节课没有讲到。
but you will learn them as time goes by. The key point is that wherever the quantity is changing,
但随着时间的推移，你会学会它们。关键的一点是，凡是量变。
derivatives will play a key role. That brings me to the end of today’s lesson.
衍生品将发挥关键作用。今天的课程到此结束。
The next lesson will talk about related rates, but before we do that, please review today’s lesson,
下一节课将讲到相关的费率，但在讲之前，请大家先回顾一下今天的课程。
go over the exercises and make sure that you understand them really well
重温练习，确保你真正理解它们
because derivatives are very import in sciences, and it’s important that you understand
因为衍生品在科学上是非常重要的，你必须要了解
how they can be used. I’ll stop over here. I hope you have enjoyed listening.
如何使用它们。我就在这里停一下。希望你听得开心。
Thank you.
谢谢你了